Guide to the Jerome J. Shestack papers, 1944-2011 and undated, bulk 1965-2000 RL.11610
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- American Bar Association, 1960-2009 and undated; Approximately 26 large boxes.
  - Sections and Committees, 1960-2009 and undated
    - Commission on the Mentally Disabled (CMD) Correspondence, 1975-1977; 4 folders (Box 14)
      Correspondence to and from Shestack regarding the ABA's Commission on the Mentally Disabled
    - Commision on the Mentally Disabled-ABA Conference, 1975 (Box 15)
    - Commission on the Mentally Disabled-Bar, 1975-1977 (Box 15)
      Correspondence from Shestack to state bar association presidents asking for their cooperation in creating a guide to advocating for the Mentally Disabled for distribution. A final guide copy is included.
    - Commission on the Mentally Disabled Backup Center, 1975 June 19 (Box 15)
      Letter from Shestack to Dean Kimball advocating for the need for a Mental Health Legal Advocacy Center
    - Commission on the Mentally Disabled Mental Health Legal Advocacy Project, 1978 (Box 15)
    - Commission on the Mentally Disabled - Institute for Continuing Care Brochure, 1998 July 15-16 (Box 79)
      Executive Summary for Quality of Life for Persons with Disabilities in the United States Institute for Continuing Care
    - Commission on the Mentally Disabled Assorted files, 1973-1997, undated; 9 folders (Box 15)
      Correspondence and annual reports about Commission on Mentally Disabled Activities and information for state bar associations on how to start a mental health committee
    - "The Mentally Disabled: A New American Bar Association Viewpoint By Jerome Shestack, 1974 Feb.2 (Box 15)
    - National Advisory Committee, 1968-1971; 2 folders (Box 15)
      Committee meeting documents and newspaper clippings regarding the committee's involvement with the California Rural Legal Assistance
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) Correspondence, 1966-1971; 3 folders (Box 15)
      Correspondence regarding work within the ABA's Office of Economic Opportunity
    - Office of Economic Opportunity Funded Data, 1966 (Box 16)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity Memoranda to National Advisory Committee, 1965-1972; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity National Justice Foundation, 1969 (Box 16)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity Source Files, 1960-1980; 4 folders (Box 16)
      Proposals, memorandums, and newsletters concerning OEO
    - Office of Economic Opportunity Legal Services, 1966-1967; 3 folders (Box 16)
      Correspondence regarding OEO Legal Services
    - Office of Economic Opportunity Administrative Files, 1971-1973; 3 folders (Box 16)
      Various reports, program files and correspondence regarding OEO administrative programs
    - Standing Committee on Law, 1998 (Box 16)
    - Standing Committee on World Order Under Law, 1996 (Box 16)
    - Standing Committee on Legal Aid and Indigent Defendants, 1980 Oct. 6, 1994 (Box 16)
    - Public Services Group, undated (Box 16)
    - Section Materials, 1992 (Box 16)
      Various correspondence discussing different section activities
    - Section of General Practice, 1991 (Box 16)
    - Section of International Law and Practice, 1990-1991 (Box 16)
    - Program Committee, 1994-1995 (Box 17)
    - American Bar Association Presidential Nominating Committee, 1993 (Box 17)
    - Ethics Task Force, 2002 May 30 (Box 17)
      Meeting information from the IBA Task Force on Profession Ethics to be used in an ABA context.
    - Task Force on Lawyer's Political Contributions, 1998 (Box 17)
    - Long Range Planning Committee Report, 1996 (Box 17)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Agenda, 1997 August 2 (Box 17)
    - Section on Judicial Administration, 1991-1992 (Box 17)
    - Special Advisory Committee on International Activities Fall Meeting Minutes, 1997 October 28; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Standing Committee on Education About Communism, 1969 (Box 17)
    - Special Committee on Judicial Independence, 1998 (Box 17)
    - Federal Judiciary Committee, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 17)
      Correspondence, memorandums, and articles collected in response to Shestack's appointment to the Federal Judiciary Committee
    - Program and Planning Committee Agendas, 1994; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - General Committee Files, 1980-1997; 3 folders (Box 17)
      Correspondence, memorandums, news clippings, and reports related to committees of ABA, kept in original order.
    - General Committee Files, 1996-1997; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Internal Reports, 1975, 1994-1999 and undated
    Files chiefly house reports circulated within the American Bar Association. The majority are administrative in nature and distributed association-wide. A few reports are specifically related to Shestack's work within the organization, such as grant reports.
    - Administrative Internal Reports, 1994-1999; 10 folders (Box 18)
      Reports circulated among ABA Members that concern administrative activities; reports not circulated to the public
    - Legal and Government Priorities Reports, 1996-1997 (Box 18)
    - State Bar Association Reports, 1996, undated (Box 18)
    - Foundations and Services Reports, 1975,1997, undated; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Internal Grant Report, 1997 Oct. 1 (Box 18)
      Grant Application/Report for ABA Justice and Education Section submitted to the American Endowment Committee
    - Promoting Professionalism Reports and Drafts, 1997 January-1998 July; 2 folders (Box 18)
      Internal reports and report Drafts that document ABA programs and initiatives to exhibit professionalism as members of the legal field.
    - Promoting Professionalism Reports and Drafts, 1997 January-1998 July; 11 folders (Box 19)
  - ABA Publications and Mailings, 1970-2005 and undated
    This subseries consists of news and promotional materials sent to all members of the American Bar Association, such as the ABA Journal or mailings about membership. Most files contain articles related to Shestack's work within the organization.
    Some related materials can be found in the Print Materials series.
    - Publications and Mailings, 1970-1997; 4 folders (Box 19)
      ABA magazines, and public mail sent to members and other people to advertise ABA and its activities
    - Publications and Mailings, 1998-2005, undated; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Publications and Mailings, 1992,1994, undated (Box 24)
  - Subject Files, 1960-2009 and undated
    Subseries includes correspondence, reports, and memoranda concerning various people and events related to Shestack's work during his time in the American Bar Association. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject name.
    - Subject Files A-I, 1960-2009 and undated; 27 folders (Box 20)
      Subject files arranged alphabetically, including but not limited to the following subjects: Chamber of Commerce, China Project, Coalition for Justice, International Criminal Court
    - Subject Files I-S, 1960-2009 and undated; 35 folders (Box 21)
      Subject files arranged alphabetically, including but not limited to the following subjects: International Criminal Court, Minorities, SACIA, Supplemental Security Income
    - Subject Files S-U, 1960-2009 and undated; 4 folders (Box 22)
      Subject Files arranged alphabetically, including Supreme Court Briefs and University of South Carolina School of Law Evaluation
  - Administrative Files, 1970-2006
    This subseries consists of files regarding administrative activities of ABA involving Shestack. Materials are mostly meeting minutes and agendas. The general administrative files contain a variety of similar administrative documents that were originally unfiled.
    - Ethics Meeting, 1999 January (Box 22)
    - Section Meeting Files, 1996 (Box 22)
    - Section Officers Files, 1995; 4 folders (Box 22)
      Files documenting section plans and profiling section officers
    - ABA Mid-Year Meeting Minutes, 1992 (Box 22)
    - Legal Program Binder Files, 1997-1998; 4 folders (Box 22)
      Files include ABA Law Day Results 1998, ABA Legal Education, Legal Intelligencer Article, Law and National Security Schedule Sheet, Judiciary Committee Files
    - Economic and Social Council Application Files, 1996 May 24; 2 folders (Box 22)
      Application from ABA submitted to the UN Committee on Non-Governmental Organizations for consultative status in category II with the Economic and Social Council
    - State Bar Directors Inquiry, 1992; 2 folders (Box 22)
      Shestack's Correspondence with state bar Directors on the status of ABA
    - Board of Governors Agenda, 1997 July-1997 August; 7 folders (Box 23)
    - Board of Governors Agenda, 1998 July 29-31; 2 folders (Box 79)
    - American Bar Endowment Director's Meeting, 1997 June; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Center for Professional Responsibility Chair Meeting Binder Files, 1997 May (Box 23)
    - General Administrative, 1972-2006; 12 folders (Box 23)
      Files that document administrative activities within ABA regarding various events and subjects. Includes agendas, reports, meeting minutes, binder notes, and some correspondence.
    - General Administrative, 1972-2006; 12 folders (Box 24)
    - General Administrative, 1970-1998; 5 folders (Box 79)
    - General Administrative, 1981-2004; 4 folders (Box 80)
- Organizations, 1961-2008 and undated; Approximately 28 large boxes.
  Series comprises materials concerning Shestack's work as a member and leader in various organizations. Materials demonstrate Shestack's passion for both human rights, the legal profession, and the intersection of the two subjects. Highlights of the series include his work within multiple organizations, particularly the International League of Human Rights, to raise awareness of the persecution of Soviet dissident Andrei Sakharov. Other highlights include his work for Jewish human rights and advocacy and his role as U.S. ambassador to the United Nations Commission on Human Rights. Formats vary across organizations, but generally consists of correspondence, subject files, reports, and administrative files.
  - International League for Human Rights, 1968-2008 and undated
    The materials in this series document Shestack's work in the International League for Human Rights (ILHR), a human rights organization of which he became and member around the time of its conception in 1963 and was chairman from 1976 until 1996. Documents include correspondence, subject files, conference proceedings, reports, newsletters, meeting minutes, and other administrative files. Most correspondence occurs between Shestack and ILHR colleagues, though some corresponce occurs between Shestack and non-ILHR members regarding collaborative work between ILHR and other organizations. Subject files are arranged in alphabetical order, and cover a variety of topics documenting Shestack's work in the organization, including files about human rights in various countries and organization funding. The materials also demonstrate Shestack's work to raise awareness of mistreatment of political dissident Andrei Sakharov and disappearances of thousands of people during the military junta in Argentina in the 1970s. The International League for Human Rights was known as the International League for the Rights of Man until it was renamed in 1976.
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1973-1974; 2 folders (Box 24)
      Contains correspondence between Shestack and his colleagues regarding his work and other activities within the International League for Human Rights.
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1974-1989; 16 folders (Box 25)
    - Administrative Correspondence, 1982, 1985-1987; 5 folders (Box 26)
      Correspondence specifically regarding ILHR responses to global events, meeting coordination,organization of reports, and collaboration with other organizations.
    - Administrative Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 80)
    - Solicitation Correspondence from Shestack, 1968, 1977, 1982, 1997; 3 folders (Box 26)
      Letters to potential donors of International League for Human Rights requesting financial support.
    - Country Ambassador Correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 80)
      Letters between Shestack and ambassadors of various countries
    - Africa, undated (Box 26)
    - Argentina, 1978-1979, 1990 March, undated; 3 folders (Box 26)
    - Austria, 1975 Dec. 15 (Box 26)
    - Awards Dinner Cassette Tapes 1-3, 1997 Sept. 16 (Box 86)
    - Background Information on ILHR, 1987 (Box 26)
    - Bellagio, 1979 (Box 26)
    - Brazil, 1972-1978 (Box 26)
    - Bulgaria, 1978 (Box 26)
    - Burlatsky, 1991 (Box 26)
    - Chile, 1976-1978, 1982; 2 folders (Box 26)
    - China, 1978, 1989; 2 folders (Box 26)
    - China Subcommittee Hearing, 1991 (Box 26)
    - Conference Reports, 1977, 1991, 1996 (Box 26)
    - Cyprus, 1976 (Box 26)
    - Czechoslovakia, 1977 (Box 26)
    - Daniel Patrick Moynihan, 1975 (Box 33)
    - Defenders Project Case Files, 1987 (Box 26)
    - Defenders Project Information, 1987 (Box 26)
    - Disappearance Reports, 1979 September 20 (Box 26)
    - Disappearance Report, undated (Box 80)
    - Disappearances Transcript, 1979 (Box 26)
    - Dominican Republic, 1978 May 18 (Box 26)
    - Donna Sullivan, 1992 (Box 26)
    - East Germany, 1983 (Box 33)
    - Egypt, 1977 (Box 26)
    - Eleanor Roosevelt, 1984, undated; 3 folders (Box 26)
      Documents about Eleanor Roosevelt that connect her human rights work with the work of the International League for Human Rights
    - El Salvador, 1978 (Box 26)
    - Ethiopia, 1977 (Box 26)
    - Fang Li Zhi Reception, 1991 (Box 27)
    - Ford Foundation Funding Application, undated (Box 27)
    - Ford Foundation Proposal Draft, undated (Box 27)
    - Foundation Funding Files, 1973-1977, 1981, undated; 2 folders (Box 27)
      Documents that detail funding needs and applications processes for funding from various foundations that wanted to contribute to the International League for Human Rights' cause.
    - Foundation Funding Files, 1984 (Box 33)
    - Geneva, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Germany Democratic Republic, 1982 (Box 27)
    - Grant Proposal for Foundation Funding, undated (Box 27)
    - Grenville Clark Prize Nomination for Shestack, 1981 June 30 (Box 27)
    - Guinea, 1977-1979 (Box 80)
    - Haiti, 1978 December 12 (Box 80)
    - Human Rights Research in the 20th Century Brochure/Program, 1990 Nov. 9-12 (Box 27)
    - Human Rights Research Files, 1973, 1980-1990, undated (Box 27)
      Documents that Shestack and his International League of Human Rights colleagues used for research specifically pertaining to the human rights work of the organization.
    - Hungary, 1977 July 31 (Box 80)
    - ICC Conference, 2008 (Box 28)
    - Human Rights Board Meeting, 1999 September 15 (Box 28)
    - India, 1976 (Box 28)
    - India, 1976-1979 (Box 80)
    - International Covenants, 1991-1995 (Box 28)
    - International Observer Mission, 1986-1987 (Box 80)
    - Iran, 1978-1979; 3 folders (Box 28)
    - Iraq, 1977 (Box 80)
    - Ireland, 1977 (Box 80)
    - Israel Affiliate, 1971-1974 (Box 80)
    - Israel, 1982 (Box 28)
    - Japan and Paraguay, 1977, 1987 (Box 80)
    - Joseph C. Wilson Award Nomination for Shestack, undated (Box 28)
    - Kurdish Situation, 1991 (Box 28)
    - Lawyers and Judges, 1985-1986 (Box 33)
    - League Support Mailing, 1989 (Box 28)
    - Lithuania, 1979 (Box 28)
    - Media Award Dinner for Rosenthal, 1991-1992 (Box 28)
    - Nicaragua, 1984-1986; 3 folders (Box 28)
    - Panama, 1975-1978 (Box 80)
    - Paraguay, 1976 July, 1979-1980; 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Paraguay, 1976-1978 (Box 80)
    - Psychiatry, 1974-1977, undated; 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Research Sources, 1971-1976, undated; 3 folders (Box 28)
      Documents used for research by Shestack and his colleagues for various work within the organization
    - Remarks on Sakharov Case by Shestack, 1980 Feb.-Mar. (Box 28)
    - Sakharov, 1973-1975, 1980-1986; 3 folders (Box 28)
      Documents pertaining to the life, work, and controversy surrounding Andrei Sakharov, a Russian nuclear physicist and human rights activist. Shestack worked against the Sakharov's mistreatment as a Soviet dissident around this time.
    - Sakharov Articles, 1984-1987; 2 folders (Box 28)
      Articles discussing Sakharov controversy and his human rights work
    - Sakharov Files and Tribute Publications, 1984, undated (Box 80)
      Includes 1984 tribute book about Andrei Sakharov and Yelena Bonner
    - Sakharov Hearing, 1983 (Box 28)
    - Sakharov Reception, 1988; 2 folders (Box 28)
      Plans for reception honoring Sakharov
    - Sakharov Reception, 1988 (Box 29)
    - Sakharov Reception Photos, 1988 (Box 80)
      Photo sheets from the Sakharov Reception
    - South Korea, 1984 (Box 29)
    - South Africa Publicity, 1978 (Box 29)
    - South Africa, 1977-1979 (Box 80)
    - Sri Lanka (Ceylon), 1974 (Box 80)
    - Syria, 1974 (Box 80)
    - Tax Protest, 1974 (Box 29)
    - Terrorism, 1985-1986 (Box 80)
    - Torture, 1976-1978 (Box 29)
    - Turkey, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Turkish Mission, 1986-1987 (Box 29)
    - Uganda, undated (Box 29)
    - Uganda, 1975-1978 (Box 80)
    - Ukraine, 1979 (Box 29)
    - U.N. Review, undated (Box 29)
    - Uruguay, 1979, 1982 (Box 29)
    - Uruguay, 1977-1978 (Box 80)
    - Uruguay and USSR, 1986 February (Box 29)
    - USSR, 1985-1987, undated; 2 folders (Box 29)
    - USSR, 1975-1978 (Box 80)
    - USSR, 1976 (Box 81)
    - Vietnam, 1976-1977 (Box 81)
    - Yugoslavia, 1984, 1990-1993; 4 folders (Box 29)
    - Yugoslavia, 1976-1977 (Box 81)
    - Zaire, 1987 (Box 29)
    - President's Message by Shestack, 1983 Sept. (Box 29)
    - Human Rights as a Condition of Peace, 1979 Nov. (Box 29)
    - Statements to ILHR Committees, 1973-1974, 1979, 1982; 2 folders (Box 29)
    - UNESCO Speech, 1979 November (Box 30)
    - Report on Neve Tirza and Ramel Prisons, Israel, 1972 Nov. (Box 30)
    - Report on Israeli League for Human and Civil Rights, undated (Box 30)
    - Report on Human Rights Defenders in Nicaragua Draft, 1986 July (Box 30)
    - Response to the Comments of Aryeh Neier, 1986 Sept 17 (Box 30)
    - Strategies Conference Report, 1979 Oct. (Box 30)
    - Northern Ireland Report, undated (Box 30)
    - Lebanon Report to UN Working Group, 1985 Sept. 12 (Box 30)
    - Report on Conference on Implementing a Human Rights Commitment in US Foreign Policy, 1977 March 4 (Box 30)
    - Human rights reports sponsored by the International League for Human Rights, 1977, 1979, undated (Box 30)
    - Annual Review, 1979-1980 (Box 30)
    - Judaism and Human Rights Brochure, 1983 (Box 30)
    - In Brief Newsletters, 1989 (Box 30)
    - In Brief Newsletters, 1988-1982 (Box 81)
    - Program for Shestack's Human Rights Award ceremony, 1997 Sept. 16 (Box 30)
    - Press Releases, 1983-1985, 1993 (Box 30)
    - News and Press Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 32)
    - Human Rights Bulletin newsletter and booklet, 1991, 1994 (Box 30)
    - Human Rights Bulletin newsletter and booklet, 1978 (Box 33)
    - Newsletters, 1983-1988 (Box 32)
    - Board of Directors file, 1979 (Box 30)
    - Board Members, 1984-1986 (Box 32)
    - Executive Committee files, 1982 (Box 30)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 1986-1989; 3 folders (Box 30)
    - Meeting Minutes and Bylaws for Board of Directors, 1982-1985; 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 1985 Sept 12 (Box 32)
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 1974-1975 (Box 33)
    - 1980 Nominating Committee Member List, 1979 (Box 30)
    - UN Meeting Agenda, 1990 Nov. (Box 30)
    - Organization Tax Exemption Files, 1973-1975; 2 folders (Box 81)
    - General Administrative Files, 1972-2004, undated; 2 folders (Box 30)
      Includes newsletters, reports booklets, agendas, some correspondence, in addition to more committee meeting minutes, commemorative files, some files used for research pertaining to the International League for Human Rights. Documents within files maintain their original order.
    - General Administrative Files, 1972-2004, undated; 23 folders (Box 31)
    - General Administrative Files, 1972-2004, undated; 19 folders (Box 32)
    - General Administrative Files, 1976-1978 (Box 33)
    - General Administrative Files, 1970-1997, undated; 6 folders (Box 81)
  - International Bar Association, 1984-2002 and undated
    The International Bar Association subseries houses materials from Shestack's time as a member of the International Bar Association. Materials document Shestack's correspondence and collaboration with other national bar association leaders across the world, particularly in regards to law's role in international human rights issues. Types of materials include correspondence, subject files, international conference files, materials from bar associations in different countries, meeting minutes, and a few publications.
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1990-1994; 1994 Feb 15; 7 folders (Box 33)
      Correspondence to and from Shestack regarding the activities of the International Bar Association
    - Human Rights Correspondence, 1993 (Box 33)
    - IBA Action Plan Correspondence, 1991 (Box 33)
    - Asian Human Rights Organization, 1993 (Box 33)
    - Buenos Aires Conference File, 1988 (Box 33)
    - Committee 19 Meeting, 1991, 1994 (Box 33)
    - Chongwe Report on Zambia, 1990 July 18 (Box 81)
    - Geneva Conference, 1994 (Box 33)
    - Human Rights Activities of Standing Committee, 1994, undated (Box 33)
    - Legal Intelligencer Article for IBA Action Plan, 1992 (Box 33)
    - Kenya, 1991, undated; 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Khajawa Case, 1993, undated (Box 81)
    - Malaysia Project, 1993-1994 (Box 33)
    - Melbourne Conference, 1992-1994 (Box 33)
    - Muna Report on Cameroon, 1990 March 27 (Box 81)
    - Murungi Report on African Charter, undated (Box 81)
    - Northern Ireland, 1993-1994, undated (Box 33)
    - Role of the Lawyer in Human Rights Issues, 1997 Feb 15 (Box 33)
    - Ruzindana: African Charter Paper, 1990 Sept. 19-25 (Box 81)
    - Second Asian Pacific Ministerial Conference on Women and Development International Bar Association Statement, 1994 June 7-14 (Box 33)
    - Section on General Practice, 1993 (Box 33)
    - World Bar Leaders Conference, 1990-1991, 1991 June 7; 4 folders (Box 33)
      Conference proceedings and administrative materials
    - World Bar Leaders Conference, 1991 June 7; 2 folders (Box 34)
    - Articles on Manila Workshop, 1994 (Box 34)
    - Manila Workshop Materials, 1994 June (Box 34)
    - Manila Workshop Correspondence, 1994 (Box 34)
    - Manila Workshop Nairman Speech, 1994 June (Box 34)
    - Country Reports, undated (Box 34)
      Reports on legal actions in various countries
    - Philippines Background Information, 1993-1994 (Box 34)
    - Philippines Meeting Notes, undated (Box 34)
    - Philippines Summary, 1993 (Box 34)
    - Protest Letters and Cases, 1992-1993; 3 folders (Box 34)
    - Australian Bar Letters, 1993 (Box 34)
    - Norwegian Bar Letters, 1993-1994 (Box 34)
    - Trial Observance Corps. Biographies, 1994, undated; 3 folders (Box 34)
    - Trial Observance Corps. Correspondence, 1994 (Box 34)
    - Trial Observance Corps. Formation and Guidelines, 1994 (Box 34)
    - Corps. Member Curriculum Vitaes, 1994 (Box 34)
    - Trial Observance Corps. Liaisons, 1994 (Box 34)
    - Trial Observers Corps. Resource File, 1994 (Box 34)
    - New York Meeting, 1990 (Box 34)
    - New Orleans Conference, 1993 (Box 34)
    - Standing Committee on Human Rights Trial Observer, 1993-1994 (Box 34)
    - Australia Council Meeting Agenda, 1994 Oct. (Box 34)
    - Human Rights Action Plan Materials, 1987-1993, undated; 3 folders (Box 35)
    - Human Rights Action Plan Protest Letter Docket, 1992 (Box 35)
    - Human Rights Fund Resolutions, 1993 (Box 35)
    - Human Rights and a Just Rule of Law Committee, undated (Box 35)
    - Committee 19 Program, Human Rights Advocacy Under Stress, 1989 Oct. 4 (Box 35)